
    <appendix>
        <title><label id="sect:3rdpartylics"/>Third-Party Licenses and Trademarks</title>
        <p>
            ecromedos incorporates or makes use of certain third-party Free and Open Source
            Software.
            All third-party product names, logos, and brands mentioned in this document
            are the property of their respective owners.
        </p>
        <section tocentry="no">
            <title>Python</title>
            <p>
                <qq>Python</qq> is a registered trademark of the Python Software Foundation. Large
            parts of ecromedos are written in the Python Programming Language. Python is licensed
            under a permissive, non-copyleft Open Source license.
            The full license text is available at
                <link url="https://www.python.org/download/releases/3.4.0/license/">https://&zwsp;www.&zwsp;python.&zwsp;org/&zwsp;download/&zwsp;releases/&zwsp;3.4.0/&zwsp;license/</link>.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section tocentry="no">
            <title>Mistune</title>
            <p>
                The <tt>md2ecml</tt> script that comes with ecromedos and which can
            translate Markdown to ecromedos Markup Language uses the Mistune
            Markdown Parser available from
            <link url="https://github.com/lepture/mistune">https://&zwsp;github.&zwsp;com/&zwsp;lepture/&zwsp;mistune</link>.
            Mistune is licensed under the following terms:
            </p>
            <verbatim strip="yes">
Copyright (c) 2014 - 2015, Hsiaoming Yang

All rights reserved.

Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are met:

* Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice,
  this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.

* Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice,
  this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation
  and/or other materials provided with the distribution.

* Neither the name of the creator nor the names of its contributors may be
  used to endorse or promote products derived from this software without
  specific prior written permission.

THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS"
AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE
ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE
LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR
CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF
SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS
INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN
CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE)
ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE
POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
            </verbatim>
        </section>
        <section tocentry="no">
            <title>Normalize.css</title>
            <p>
            ecromedos uses Normalize.css available from
                <link url="https://necolas.github.io/normalize.css/">https://&zwsp;necolas.&zwsp;github.&zwsp;io/&zwsp;normalize.css/</link>.
            Normalize.css is licensed under the MIT license as follows:
            </p>
            <verbatim strip="yes">
The MIT License (MIT)

Copyright © Nicolas Gallagher and Jonathan Neal

Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy of
this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"), to deal in
the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights to
use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies
of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is furnished to do
so, subject to the following conditions:

The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in all
copies or substantial portions of the Software.

THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE
SOFTWARE.
            </verbatim>
        </section>
        <section tocentry="no">
            <title>Pygments</title>
            <p>
                ecromedos directly interfaces with Pygments available from
                    <link url="http://pygments.org">http://&zwsp;pygments.&zwsp;org</link>.
                Pygments is licensed under a simplified BSD license as follows:
            </p>
            <verbatim strip="yes">
Copyright (c) 2006-2015 by the respective authors (see AUTHORS file).
All rights reserved.

Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are
met:

* Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
  notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.

* Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
  notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the
  documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.

THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
"AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR
A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT
LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE,
DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY
THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT
(INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE
OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
            </verbatim>
        </section>
        <section tocentry="no">
            <title>libxml2 and libxslt</title>
            <p>
                ecromedos uses libxml2 and libxslt available from
                    <link url="http://xmlsoft.org">http://&zwsp;xmlsoft.&zwsp;org</link>.
                Both libraries are licensed under the MIT license:
            </p>
            <verbatim strip="yes">
Except where otherwise noted in the source code (e.g. the files hash.c,
list.c and the trio files, which are covered by a similar licence but
with different Copyright notices) all the files are:

 Copyright (C) 1998-2012 Daniel Veillard.  All Rights Reserved.

Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy
of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"), to deal
in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights
to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell
copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is fur-
nished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in
all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FIT-
NESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN
THE SOFTWARE.
            </verbatim>
        </section>
        <section tocentry="no">
            <title>Lxml</title>
            <p>
                ecromedos uses Lxml, a Pythonic wrapper around libxml2 and libxslt,
            available from <link url="http://lxml.de">http://lxml.de</link>.
            Lxml is licensed under a BSD license as follows:
            </p>
            <verbatim strip="yes">
Copyright (c) 2004 Infrae. All rights reserved.

Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are
met:

  1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
     notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
   
  2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
     notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
     the documentation and/or other materials provided with the
     distribution.

  3. Neither the name of Infrae nor the names of its contributors may
     be used to endorse or promote products derived from this software
     without specific prior written permission.

THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
"AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR
A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL INFRAE OR
CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL,
EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO,
PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR
PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF
LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
            </verbatim>
        </section>
    </appendix>

