
    <chapter>
        <title><label id="sect:installation"/>Installation</title>
        <p>
            This chapter explains how to install and configure ecromedos on your system.
        The latest version of ecromedos can always be obtained from the project website
        at <link url="http://ecromedos.net"><tt>http://&zwsp;www.&zwsp;ecromedos.&zwsp;net</tt></link>.
        </p>
        <section>
            <title>Dependencies<label id="sect:dependencies"/></title>
            <p>
                ecromedos is developed on Debian/GNU Linux, but should run on any system which offers
            the following dependencies:
            </p>
            <dl>
                <dt>Python 3</dt>
                <dd>
                        A powerful scripting language. Python is available for all popular operating
                    systems and can be obtained from the website of the Python Software Foundation
                    at <link url="http://python.org"><tt>http://&zwsp;www.&zwsp;python.&zwsp;org</tt></link>.
                    ecromedos requires a recent version of Python 3 to run. Using ecromedos with Python 2 is
                    not officially supported anymore, your mileage may vary.
                </dd>
                <dt>libxml and libxslt</dt>
                <dd>
                        Two super fast and stable libraries for processing XML, developed by Daniel
                    Veillard for the GNOME project. The project homepage is located at
                    <link url="http://www.xmlsoft.org"><tt>http://&zwsp;www.&zwsp;xmlsoft.&zwsp;org</tt></link>.
                </dd>
                <dt>lxml</dt>
                <dd>
                    A pythonic binding to libxml and libxslt implementing the Element Tree API with
                    extensions. The project homepage is located at <link url="http://lxml.de"><tt>http://lxml.de</tt></link>.
                </dd>
                <dt>Imagemagick</dt>
                <dd>
                        A set of tools for image manipulation. ecromedos uses Imagemagick for
                    resizing bitmap images and for format conversions. You can download the 
                    software from
                    <link url="http://imagemagick.org"><tt>http://&zwsp;www.&zwsp;imagemagick.&zwsp;org</tt></link>.
                </dd>
                <dt>&tex;</dt>
                <dd>
                        If you want to produce PostScript or PDF, you need an installation of the
                    &tex; typesetting system. It is recommended that you use a recent version of &tex; Live,
                    available from
                    <link url="http://www.tug.org/texlive/"><tt>http://&zwsp;www.&zwsp;tug.&zwsp;org/&zwsp;texlive/</tt></link>.
                    Make sure to install language packs for the languages that you are going to
                    write in.
                </dd>
                <dt>dvipng</dt>
                <dd>
                        A utility to convert DVI files to PNG or GIF bitmaps. ecromedos uses dvipng
                    to convert mathematical formulas to bitmap graphics when generating XHTML output.
                    dvipng is available from <link url="http://www.nongnu.org/dvipng/"><tt>http://&zwsp;www.&zwsp;nongnu.&zwsp;org/&zwsp;dvipng/</tt></link>,
                    it may also be included in your &tex; distribution.
                </dd>
                <dt>Pygments</dt>
                <dd>
                        Pygments is a powerful syntax highlighter that can lex a vast amount of
                    programming languages and scripts. ecromedos uses Pygments for automatic syntax
                    highlighting of code samples. Find out more about Pygments at
                    <link url="http://pygments.org"><tt>http://&zwsp;pygments.&zwsp;org</tt></link>.
                </dd>
            </dl>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Installation from Source</title>
            <p>
                First of all, double-check that you have installed the dependencies listed in section
            <ref idref="sect:dependencies"/>.
            </p>
            <minisection>
                <title>Step <counter group="inst_step" simple="yes"/>: Unpacking the Tarball</title>
                <p>
                     ecromedos can be installed anywhere in the file system. It is recommended,
                however, that you place it in <tt>/opt</tt>. In order to do so, open a shell
                and become superuser root by typing
                </p>
                <listing>
                    <code syntax="bash" strip="yes">
su -
                    </code>
                </listing>
                <p>            
                    Then change your working directory to <tt>/opt</tt>
                </p>
                <listing>
                    <code syntax="bash" strip="yes">
cd /opt
                    </code>
                </listing>
                <p>
                    and unpack the tarball. The following example assumes that the tarball
                resides in the home directory of system user tobias:
                </p>
                <listing>
                    <code syntax="bash" strip="yes">
tar -xvzf ~tobias/ecromedos-x.y.z.tar.gz
                    </code>
                </listing>
            </minisection>
            <minisection>
                <title>Step <counter group="inst_step" simple="yes"/>: Adding the Executable to the System Path</title>
                <p>
                    Now change to <tt>/usr/local/bin</tt> and create a symbolic link to the
                main executable:
                </p>
                <listing>
                    <code syntax="bash" strip="yes">
cd /usr/local/bin
ln -s /opt/ecromedos-x.y.z/bin/ecromedos
                    </code>
                </listing>
                <p>
                    By placing this link in the system path, you will be able to call
                ecromedos by name without having to enter the canonical path to the
                executable.
                </p>
            </minisection>
            <minisection>
                <title>Step <counter group="inst_step" simple="yes"/>: Pre-compiling the Source Files</title>
                <p>
                    Since you would typically install ecromedos in a location to which
                unprivileged users don't have write access, you should pre-compile the
                Python source files to bytecode, so that users can benefit from faster
                start-up times. In order to do so, go into the installation directory
                and issue the following command:
                </p>
                <listing>
                    <code syntax="bash" strip="yes">
find . -name "*.py" -exec \
    python -c "import py_compile; py_compile.compile('{}')" \;
                    </code>
                </listing>
            </minisection>
            <minisection>
                <title>Step <counter group="inst_step" simple="yes"/>: Adapting the Configuration</title>
                <p>
                    Having completed the installation procedure described above, you may now want to
                edit the configuration file <tt>ecmds.conf</tt>, which is located in the <tt>etc</tt>
                subdirectory below the installation folder. ecromedos is designed to be relocatable,
                so in many cases it should just work out of the box. However, ecromedos interfaces
                with a number of third-party programs whose installation paths may differ between platforms.
                Pay particular attention to all configuration parameter names ending in <tt>_bin</tt> or
                <tt>_dir</tt>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Parameter values can be reused in arguments to other settings by prefixing the
                name of the parameter to be referenced with a dollar sign. For instance, if
                <tt>base_dir</tt> is set to
                </p>
                <listing>
                    <code syntax="text" strip="yes">
/opt/ecromedos-x.y.z/
                    </code>
                </listing>
                <p>
                    then you can set <tt>lib_dir</tt> to
                </p>
                <listing>
                    <code syntax="text" strip="yes">
/opt/ecromedos-x.y.z/lib
                    </code>
                </listing>
                <p>
                    by simply writing
                </p>
                <listing>
                    <code syntax="text" strip="yes">
lib_dir = $base_dir/lib
                    </code>
                </listing>
                <p>
                    ecromedos version 2 introduced the automatic variable <tt>$install_dir</tt>,
                which is always available and contains the path to the installation directory.
                </p>
            </minisection>
        </section>
    </chapter>

