
    <chapter>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <p>
            If you are the type of person whom the typical word processor drives out
        of their mind. If your blood pressure goes up when a program tries
        to be smart about every single key press you make, even interpreting the
        backspace key in a myriad of ways that you never expected. Or if you find
        yourself spending more time on reformatting your documents than doing actual
        writing, then ecromedos might be just for you.
        </p>
        <p>
            This is about a piece of software that can change your life as
        a technical writer and restore your belief in the power of the backspace key
        for good. Making use of modern technologies, but building on proven concepts
        that stem from the early days of computing, ecromedos is a text processing system
        of a different kind. If you are ready to break with old habits and willing to
        learn something new, then hopefully you will find that ecromedos can render you
        more productive by letting you focus on writing, and nothing else.
        </p>
        <section>
            <title>What is it?<label id="lbl:whatisit"/></title>
            <p>
                ecromedos is an integrated solution for XML-based publishing in print and
            on the Web. It is primarily targeted at, but not limited to, the creation of
            technical documentation in the field of Computer Science. Documents are written
            in a semantic markup language and converted to representational formats with a
            dedicated processing toolchain. ecromedos supports the target formats
            XHTML and &latex;, where the latter can be compiled into high-quality PostScript
            and PDF via the &tex;<footnote>More information on &tex; and &latex; can be
            found on the <i>Comprehensive &tex; Archive Network</i> at
            <link url="http://www.ctan.org"><tt>http://&zwsp;www.&zwsp;ctan.&zwsp;org</tt></link>.</footnote>
            typesetting system.
            </p>
            <p>
                The <i>ecromedos Markup Language</i> (ECML) is modelled closely after HTML
            with some ideas and additional elements borrowed from &latex;. It allows you to
            compose comprehensive, well-structured documents from a comparably small set of
            language elements. Users who are already familiar with HTML or document markup
            languages like DocBook will find learning ECML particularly easy.
            </p>
            <p>
                The <i>ecromedos Document Processor</i> (EDP) uses XSL Transformations
            (XSLT) to convert source documents from ECML to the supported output formats.
            In addition, the EDP contains a special pre-processor, which operates
            directly on the XML-DOM tree of a document and carries out additional
            preparational tasks that cannot be implemented with bare XSLT, such as the
            conversion of images to processable formats or on-the-fly syntax-highlighting of
            source code listings.
            </p>
            <p>
                ecromedos is well-suited for environments where many writers collaborate on
            many documents. Since documents are written in a semantic markup language,
            writers do not have to worry much about following a style guide. There is very
            little coordination required in achieving a consistent layout and look
            over an entire range of documents, because the layouting and formatting is done
            automatically by the EDP and assorted tools during the conversion to
            representational formats.
            </p>
        </section>
            <section>
                <title>Changes in Version 2</title>
                <p>
                    Version 2 saw significant cleanups in the DTD, the XSL stylesheets and
                improved styling of HTML output via CSS. The table model was enhanced
                to support block elements in table cells and to allow splitting table cells
                into subtables. This version also introduced support for automatic
                generation of glossary and keyword indexes.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Changes in Version 2.1</title>
                <p>
                    Since version 2.1, Pygments<footnote>The Pygments homepage is located at <link
                url="http://pygments.org"><tt>http://pygments.org</tt></link>.</footnote>
                has replaced the old, built-in syntax highlighter. Pygments supports lexing a
                vast amount of programming languages and scripts and is a very mature and
                robust product.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Changes in Version 3</title>
                <p>
                    After years of collecting dust, ecromedos has been ported to Python 3 and
                modernized for the era of wide-screen displays and handheld devices. In this version,
                support for annotations in the margin had to be dropped for practical reasons. This is
                the only backward-incompatible change. Apart from that, documents written for version
                2 should translate without problems.
                </p>
            </section>
        <section>
            <title>Licensing</title>
            <p>
                ecromedos is both Free and Open Source Software, published under
            the permissive MIT license <cite idref="bib:MIT88"/>. This means that you can
            modify it, re-distribute it and use it in your own software projects without
            restrictions.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>About this Document</title>
            <p>
                This document describes the installation and usage of ecromedos and the
            scope of the ecromedos Markup Language. After reading this manual, you will be
            able to write feature-rich documents and translate them to representational
            on-screen or printable formats with the ecromedos Document Processor.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                <p>
                    In chapter <ref idref="sect:installation"/>, you will find instructions for
                downloading and installing ecromedos to your system.
                </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                <p>
                    Chapter <ref idref="sect:generalusage"/> teaches you the basics of
                starting a new document and transforming documents to representational formats.
                </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                <p>
                    After reading chapter <ref idref="sect:writingdocuments"/>, you will know
                how to write simple documents, do basic text-formatting and work with
                cross-references and counters.
                </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                <p>
                    Chapter <ref idref="sect:liststablesfigures"/> introduces more
                advanced language constructs for settings lists, figures, tables and
                mathematical formulas.
                </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                <p>
                    Chapter <ref idref="sect:backmatter"/> covers everything related to
                the backmatter of a document, including how to keep a bibliography, how to cite
                from it, and how to generate glossary and keywords indexes.
                </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                <p>
                    Chapter <ref idref="sect:styling"/> explains how to create your own
                style definitions to change the appearance of rendered ouput.
                </p>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>
                Many thanks to <nobr>Prof. Dr. Heinz-Erich Erbs</nobr> from the <link
            url="http://www.h-da.de">University of Applied Sciences in Darmstadt, Germany</link>
            for his support and advice when work on the first version of ecromedos started
            more than 10 years ago.
            </p>
            <p>
                A big <qq>thank you</qq> goes out to the makers of libxml, libxslt and the lxml
            module for writing a phantastic set of libraries for processing XML, to Guido van
            Rossum and the Python Software Foundation for a beautiful scripting language and to
            Donald Knuth for giving us superb typesetting.
            </p>
            <p>
                Thanks to everybody working on Free Software. Your stuff is a lot of fun!
            </p>
        </section>
    </chapter>

